{"tossups": [{"question": "One leader of this country wanted to create a buffer state called \u201cIntermarium\u201d out of his country and its neighbors. This country, which lost a plebiscite awarding control of the Teschen district, defeated an invading force under Marshal Tukachevsky; the key battle of that campaign took place in this country\u2019s capital and was nicknamed the \u201cMiracle on the Vistula\u201d. For ten points, name this country led by Jozef Pilsudski.", "answer": "<b> Poland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This initiative supplanted Directive 1067 and was in turn replaced by the Mutual Security Agency. This initiative was adopted after Herbert Hoover noted that a \u201cpastoral state\u201d would be the outcome of the opposing Morgenthau Plan. Greece and Turkey were the first countries to adopt this plan, and Joseph Stalin ordered Warsaw Pact nations not to accept its money. Harry Truman\u2019s Secretary of State names, for ten points, what American plan that offered economic aid to Europe after World War II?", "answer": "<b> Marshall</b> Plan (or<b> European Recovery Program</b>; accept<b> ERP</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a novel written in this language, Bartlebooth spends a decade learning how to paint before going on a trip around the world. Another novel in this language was written entirely without the use of the letter E as part of the Oulipo movement.<em> Life: A User\u2019s Manual</em> and<em> A Void</em> were written by Georges Perec in, for ten points, what language in which<em> The Stranger</em> and<em> No Exit</em> were written by Jean-Paul Sartre and Albert Camus?", "answer": "<b> French</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "During this year, the USS<em> Vandalia</em> faced off against German ships in Samoa until it was destroyed by a cyclone. The Enabling Act was signed during it to split the Dakota Territory, and the \u201cSooners\u201d and\u201cBoomers\u201d flooded to settle Oklahoma in this year. The Great Johnstown Flood devastated Pennsylvania during it, the first year where the \u201cBillion Dollar Congress\u201d met. For ten points, name this year in which Benjamin Harrison began his term as US President.", "answer": "<b> 1889</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Shuck Yee invented a machine to mass produce these things, which Seiichi Kito claims were inspired by the Omikuji tradition. A tea garden was said to have been the venue where the first of these were served in the 1890\u2019s; that example was allegedly baked in San Francisco. Sesame seed oil is generally used to make, for ten points, what foodstuff that was notably not invented in China and contains a supposed prophecy on a paper slip?", "answer": "<b> fortune cookie</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. This action, as proposed in UN Resolution 181, was rejected by one side of the discussion. Haganah and the Irgun agitated for this action, whose early advocates included Theodor Herzl. The Balfour Declaration established British support for this action, whose eventual realization led to an outpouring of hundreds of thousands of refugees from the West Bank. A 1948 war accompanied, for ten points, what geopolitical action that followed the end of the British Mandate for Palestine?", "answer": "<b> creation</b> of<b> Israel</b> (accept equivalent descriptions; accept descriptions of<b> separate states for Jews and Palestinians</b> (or<b> Jews and Arabs</b>, etc.) in Israel/Middle East) (9) This man ordered that the government store its funds in vaults rather than banks as part of the independent treasury he created. The popularity of this man plummeted after Charles Ogle accused him of lavish spending in the Gold Spoon Oration. This man was forced to carry out his predecessor\u2019s Specie Circular executive order, leading to the Panic of 1837. For ten points, name this Democratic president, a Dutch-American from New York. ANSWER: Martin<b> van Buren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An interregnum in this empire was resolved at the Battle of Camurlu. A rebellion against this empire was led by one of its former generals, Skanderbeg. This country\u2019s government was known as the Sublime Porte and was once based in Edirne. One ruler of this country, Bayezid the Thunderbolt, was captured by Timur at the Battle of Ankara. For ten points, name this empire that was led by Murad II and other sultans from modern Turkey.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A governor of this state was chairman of Hillary Clinton\u2019s 2008 bid for the presidency and controversially tried to restore the voting rights of more than 200,000 felons in an executive order that was later overturned. Democratic blocs in Fairfax and Arlington counties have made this state increasingly blue in recent elections. A senator from this state was chosen as the running mate for Hillary Clinton in the 2016 presidential election. Tim Kaine represents, for ten points, what state where state law prevents governors from serving consecutive terms in Richmond?", "answer": "<b> Virginia</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This language\u2019s 7th century Kufic style of calligraphy is based on straight lines and right angles. Like other languages in its family, including Hebrew, this language builds words around three-consonant roots. The \u201cModern Standard\u201d variety of this language is commonly used in literature and the news, despite the wide variance in dialects. This language\u2019s writing system lends its name to the term abjad, for an alphabet without vowels. For ten points, name this primary language spoken in Morocco, Egypt, and Qatar.", "answer": "<b> Arabic</b> (or al-<b>\u2018arabiyyah</b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Linguistics"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was advised by Mikhail Speransky during his reform of the government and Aleksey Arakcheev during his military reforms. This leader\u2019s failures as commander in chief</b> <b>led him to appoint Mikhail (+)</b> <b>Kutuzov to lead his army. Confusion over who should</b> <b>succeed this man led to the liberal (*)</b> Decembrist revolt. This ruler formed the Holy Alliance with Austria and Prussia to preserve Europe after the Congress of Vienna. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who led his country through the Napoleonic Wars.", "answer": "<b> Alexander I</b> of Russia", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man supposedly introduced his friend and former classmate James Madison to his future wife Dolley Payne. Anthony Merry and James Wilkinson were alleged co-conspirators in this man\u2019s plot to take over (+) land in the southwest to form his own country. This man represented New York in the Senate after winning an election against Philip (*) </b> Schuyler [sky-ler], the father-in-law of a man who thwarted this man\u2019s presidential ambitions by backing Thomas Jefferson in the election of 1800. For ten points, name this politician who won a duel against his rival, Alexander Hamilton.", "answer": "Aaron<b> Burr</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This is the most populous city founded by James Robertson, who helped lead the Watauga Association. The inhabitant of a famous residence in this city married a woman he met here named Rachel (+) Donelson. The Hermitage is located in this city, where a $1 million grant led to the 1873 creation of a (*)</b> university named for a New York tycoon. Andrew Jackson lived much of his life in, for ten points, what city which is home to Vanderbilt University, located in Tennessee?", "answer": "<b> Nashville</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "7 bunkers per square kilometer were constructed in this</b> <b>country, whose government justified it as preparation against a joint (+)</b> <b>NATO-Warsaw</b> <b>Pact invasion. After a disagreement, Nikita Khrushchev withdrew grain shipments from this country, which broke with its last ally, China, over the Three Worlds Theory. This country, the (*) </b> poorest in Europe during the 1980s, proclaimed itself the world\u2019s first atheist state. For ten points, name this isolationist Balkan nation once led by Enver Hoxha [ho-cha].", "answer": "<b> Albania</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This country birthed a tradition of musical composition known as \u201ckuchkism.\u201d Numerous works written in this country, including</b><em><b> Ruslan and Lyudmila</b></em><b> and</b><em><b> Kashchey the Immortal</b></em><b>,</b> <b>use the (+)</b> <b>whole tone scale to give a sense of foreboding evil, a technique developed by</b> <b>whole tone scale to give a sense of foreboding evil, a technique developed by</b> <b>a group that included Cesar Cui and was led by Mily (*)</b> <b>a group that included Cesar Cui and was led by Mily (*)</b> Balakirev. For ten points, name this country where nationalism was promoted by The Mighty Handful, a group of five composers including Modest Mussorgsky, Alexander Borodin, and Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b> (do not accept Soviet Union)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}